GITHAIGA KAIRUTHI Nairobi, Kenya

Nationality: Kenyan

Age: 23yrs

+254 740 129 131

githaigakairuthi56@gmail.com

Summary

My name is Githaiga Kairuthi. I am a Python and React engineer creating modern web applications. My values are unit testing, clean code, and automation in all areas of the software development lifecycle. I have 2+ years of experience delivering solutions using Python, Django, and React.

You can find some code samples, designs, and creations of mine over at my <u>GitHub</u>. I'm also interested in hearing of new opportunities, partnering up with another developer, or making new friends!

Education

MOUNT KENYA UNIVERSITY

SEPT 2017 - DEC 2021

Bachelor of Science | Business Information technology.

Work Experience

SAMIS / Full Stack Developer

AUG 2021 – SEPT 2022

RESPONSIBILITIES

- Created website prototypes using **Figma** and **Photoshop**.
- Developed websites from front to backend using REACT framework and Python (Django Rest Framework).
- Designed complex database queries using **Django ORM** modules.
- Automated repetitive tasks using **Python** Scripts.
- Worked on Django Signals, Celery and RabbitMQ queues.
- Created multiple **docker** containers and managed load balancing between them with **TRAEFIK**.

- Integrated crucial third-party APIs into the system.
- Reduced excessive use of third-party libraries by creating reusable components in REACT.
- Worked on ensuring that the system is highly scalable.
- Worked on restful microservices with FASTAPI, Django and Flask.
- Reduced excessive use of third-party libraries by creating reusable components.
- Enhanced user experience and accomplished webpage objectives by creating site structure, navigation, filtering, page optimization, and graphics integration.
- Implemented enhancements that improved web functionality and responsiveness across multiple platforms.

Environments include: - Python3, Django, Django Rest Framework, Flask, FastAPI, React.js, Redux, Next.js, HTML5/ CSS3/SCSS, Postgres, AWS, Google Cloud, PyCharm, Microsoft Visual Code.

CAMARA/ Networking Assistant

JULY 2020 - JAN 2021

- Worked in a fantastic team of professionals to install networking infrastructure in government schools around Mombasa, Kenya.
- Troubleshooted and re-configure faulty networking equipment.

NATIONAL HEALTH INSURANCE FUND(NHIF)/ Ict Intern

JAN 2019 - APRIL 2019

- Worked with a team of great professionals in the IT department of NHIF.
- Computer network installation and troubleshooting.
- Computer hardware repair and maintenance.
- Installation of computer software such as operating systems.
- Recovery of lost, deleted or corrupt computer data.
- Installation and managing servers.

Skills

Languages

- ✓ Python
- ✓ JavaScript ES5/ ES6+

Frame Works

- ✓ React/ Next.js
- ✓ Angular
- ✓ Vue
- ✓ Django
- ✓ Flask
- ✓ FastAPI

OS

- ✓ Linux/MacOS/Windows
- ✓ Visual Studio Code
- ✓ Git & GitHub

Databases

- ✓ Postgres
- ✓ MySQL
- ✓ AWS S3

Web Technologies

- ✓ HTML5/CSS3
- ✓ SCSS
- ✓ Redux

Tools & IDE

- ✓ Docker
- ✓ Kubernetes
- ✓ Docker Swarm
- ✓ Nginx
- ✓ Traefik
- ✓ CI/CD TOOLS
- ✓ Postman
- ✓ AWS
- ✓ PyCharm

Languages

Swahili, English

Projects

CUSTOM RUG HOUSE

Project Description

This project entails designing and building a full ecommerce web app and management system for a rug selling business.

Customers can access the products page anonymously but require authentication as they proceed to checkout.

Staff can add, update or delete the product information.

Customers also get relevant recommendations as per their product search information.

See the Repo Demo

Some of the Implementations include and not limited

- Implemented asynchronous actions and used axios to send requests to the backend.
- The backend is a RESTful API designed using Django Rest Framework while the frontend uses React.js implementing redux for state management.
- Used Django Sessions to manage the cart.
- Used the Backend for Frontend (BFF) architecture for scalability.
- Developed reusable front-end components (footers, side nav, headers etc.) using **React.js.**
- Used redux for state management.
- Used yarn for JavaScript package management.
- Integrated Kenyan payment service Mpesa for ease of payment.
- Implemented Google Places API integration for delivery address.

OTHER PROJECTS INCLUDE

- A CLI Tool named "moovys" for scraping upcoming movies from multiple websites (I watch movies (:-D).
- Rental Management System.
- Python project templates with support for Docker, Pytest, and more.
 Many more projects/experiments on <u>GitHub</u>